Guide to the Black Lizard Press Archive, 1977-1994
Department of Special Collections
Black Lizard Press Archive,
1977-1994
Special Collections M0932
Black Lizard Press
2.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1997.
Historical Note
In 1976 in Berkeley, California Don Ellis formed the Creative Arts Book Company. Later that year, Don Ellis met Barry Gifford, an author inspired by the nihilistic and violent side of the American dream presented in the crime fiction of the 1940's and 50's. Gifford later wrote Wild at Heart, the inspiration for the David Lynch movie of the same title. Shortly thereafter, Gifford became a consultant to the Creative Arts Book Company which gradually reprinted works by Huxley, Stein, Forster, and Kazantzakis. The Black Lizard imprint first appeared in 1980 when Ellis printed Gifford's novel Port Tropique: a story about the protagonist's involvement with smugglers and revolutionaries in Central America. Ellis, however, began to focus on more commercial ventures and Gifford drifted away, eventually ending up in France. In 1983, Gifford found a dozen novels in a Parisian bookstore by a forgotten American crime novelist, Jim Thompson. Upon returning to the states, Gifford discovered that none of Thompson's books had been in print since shortly before his death in 1977. With Gifford as the founding editor, the Black Lizard imprint was resurrected to serve the gritty criminal ethos of fifties pulp, including the tawdry stylized covers. Black Lizard went on to print 82 titles including two anthologies edited by Barry Gifford; new works by authors such as Murray Sinclair; reprints of the works of Jim Thompson, David Goodis, James M. Cain, Gertrude Stein; and the obscure, sophisticated thrillers of Charles Willeford. Black Lizard and Barry Gifford were, in fact, instrumental to the revival of the lurid romans noir. The revival carried over into film as well, with several of Thompson's stories being adapted for the screen (Grifters, and The Getaway) as well as Gifford's own Wild at Heart. For his editorial work, Gifford received the Max Perkins award from PEN West. In 1990, Don Ellis sold Black Lizard Press, including the 30 unprinted titles to which the rights had been secured, to Vintage Books. The sole exception in this sale were the rights to Port Tropique, which were retained by the author, Barry Gifford.
Scope and Content
The collection contains information regarding 81 of Black Lizard's 82 titles, with the exception being Elliot Chaze's Black Wings has my Angel. The 170 folders are arranged alphabetically in four record storage boxes by book title. Though the order of the folders was changed, the original division of content amongst the folders, as well as their titles and sub-titles, was maintained. Folders without sub-titles usually contain information regarding contracts, copies of the contracts themselves, and other item regarding aspects of production. They are fairly synonymous with folders sub-titled "production." Reviews, press releases, advertisements, photographs, other legal correspondences, and personal correspondences are included in separate folders and marked accordingly. The collection also includes two posters: a poster of the Black Lizard logo advertising the press itself and a poster with the cover art from You Only Live Twice. The collection does not contain information regarding the broader business practices and situation (financial records, advertising practices, employee information, etc.) of The Creative Arts Book Company or The Black Lizard Press. It is confined to information regarding the books themselves.
Access Terms
Alter, Robert Edmund.; Brown, Frederic.; Cain, James M.; Cain, Paul.; Carco, Francis.; Causey, James O.; Ellis, Don.; Fischer, Steve.; Gifford, Barry.; Goodis, David.; Gorman, Ed.; Heath, W.L.; Knight, Eric.; Lutz, John.; Malzberg, Barry.; Marlowe, Dan.; Nelson, Kent.; Nichols, Victoria.; Nielsen, Helen.; Nisbet, Jim.; Pronzini, Bill.; Rabe, Peter.; Simon, Roger L.; Sinclair, Murray.; Sorocco, Sin.; Stein, Gertrude.; Thompson, Jim.; Thompson, Susan.; White, Lionel.; Whittington, Harry.; Willeford, Charles.; Williams, Charles.; American literature--20th century.; Detective and mystery stories.; Printing--United States.
Container List
- After Dark, My Sweet, Jim Thompson 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agreement to Kill, Peter Rabe 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Alcoholics, Jim Thompson 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The Baby Doll Murders, James O. Causey 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Black Friday, David Goodis 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Black Mass of Brother Springer, Charles Willeford 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Black Lizard Anthology, Ed Gorman, ed. Production 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Black Lizard Anthology, Ed Gorman, ed. Reviews/Press Releases 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Second Black Lizard Anthology, Ed Gorman, ed. Reviews 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Blood Dance, Lansdale 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Blood on the Dining Room Floor, Gertrude Stein 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Blood on the Dining Room Floor, Gertrude Stein; Press Releases 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Blood on the Dining Room Floor, Gertrude Stein; Reviews, Etc. 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Blood on the Dining Room Floor; Gertrude Stein; Reviews, Etc. 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Blood on the Dining Room Floor, Gertrude Stein; Correspondence 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Blood on the Dining Room Floor, Gertrude Stein; Correspondence On Copyright 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- The Box, Peter Rabe 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Burglar, David Goodis 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Burnt Orange Heresy, Charles Willeford 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Burnt Orange Heresy, Charles Willeford 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Burnt Orange Heresy, Charles Willeford; Reviews and Press Release 1987 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Burnt Orange Heresy, Charles Willeford; Production 1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Carny Kill, Robert Edmund Alter 1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Cassidy's Girl, David Goodis 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Cassidy's Girl, David Goodis; Reviews 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Coffin & Co., Roger L. Simon 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Coffin & Co., Roger L. Simon; Production None (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Coffin & Co., Roger L. Simon; Reviews 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Coffin & Co.; Roger L. Simon; Letters 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Cockfighter, Charles Willeford 1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Cockfighter, Charles Willeford 1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Cockfigher, Charles Willeford; Reviews and Press Release 1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Cockfighter, Charles Willeford; Production 1987 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- The Criminal, Jim Thompson 1985 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- The Criminal, Jim Thompson; Reviews 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Cropper's Cabin, Jim Thompson 1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Cropper's Cabin, Jim Thompson; Reviews 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- The Damned Don't Die, Jim Nisbet 1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- The Damned Don't Die, Jim Nisbet; Reviews 1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Dead Meet, Roger L. Simon 1987 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Dead Meet, Roger L. Simon; Reviews 1989 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Death Puppet, Jim Nisbet 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Death Puppet, Jim Nisbet 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Death Puppet, Jim Nisbet; Reviews 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Detour, Helen Nielsen 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Detour, Helen Nielsen; Reviews 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Detour, Helen Nielsen; Production 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The Devil Wears Wings, Harry Whittington 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Doctor Syntax, Michael Petracca 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Doctor Syntax, Michael Petracca; Reviews 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Dig My Grave Deep, Peter Rabe 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- The Far Cry, Frederic Brown 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- The Far Cry, Frederic Brown; Reviews 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Fast One, Paul Cain; Production: Seven Slayers, Paul Cain; Production 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Fast One, Paul Cain; Reviews 1988 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Fires that Destroy, Harry Whittington 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Fires that Destroy, Harry Whittington; Production 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Forgive Me, Killer, Harry Whittington 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Forgive Me, Killer, Harry Whittington; Reviews and Press Release 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Forgive Me, Killer, Harry Whittington; Production 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Frenzy, James O. Causey 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- The Getaway, Jim Thompson 1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- The Getaway, Jim Thompson; Advertising 1984 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- The Getaway, Jim Thompson; Reviews 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Goodbye L. A., Murray Sinclair 1987 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Goodbye L. A., Murray Sinclair; Reviews 1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Goodbye L. A.; Murray Sinclair; Production 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- The Grifters, Jim Thompson 1984 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- A Hell of a Woman, Jim Thompson 1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- A Hell of a Woman, Jim Thompson; Advertising 1984 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- A Hell of a Woman, Jim Thompson; Reviews 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- His Name was Death, Frederic Brown 1986 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Ill Wind, W. L. Heath 1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Ill Wind, W. L. Heath; Production 1987 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- I Woke Up Screaming, Steve Fischer 1987 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- I Woke Up Screaming, Steve Fischer; Reviews 1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- I Woke Up Screaming; Steve Fischer; Production 1988 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Its My Funeral, Peter Rabe 1987 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Jealous Woman, James M. Cain 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- The Killing, Lionel White; Reviews No Date (Box 2, Folder 39)
- The Killing, Lionel White; Production 1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Kill the Boss Goodbye 1987 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Lethal Injection, Jim Nisbet 1987 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Lethal Injection, Jim Nisbet; Reviews 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Lethal Injection, Jim Nisbet; Production 1987 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Lethal Injection, Jim Nisbet; Photo, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Low Bite, Sin Sorocco 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Low Bite, Sin Sorocco 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Low Bite, Sin Sorocco; Reviews 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Low Bite, Sin Sorocco; Correspondence with the Author 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Man on the Run, Charles Williams 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Masques, Bill Pronzini 1986 and 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- A Moment to Prey, Harry Whittington 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- A Moment to Prey, Harry Whittington; Reviews No Date (Box 3, Folder 8)
- A Moment to Prey, Harry Whittington; Productions 1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Name of the Game is Death, Dan Marlowe 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Name of the Game is Death, Dan Marlowe; Reviews No Date (Box 3, Folder 11)
- The Name of the Game is Death, Dan Marlowe; Production 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Never Live Twice, Dan Marlowe 1986 and 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Never Live Twice, Dan Marlowe; Reviews No Date (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Never Live Twice, Dan Marlowe; Production 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Nightfall, David Goodis 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Nightfall, David Goodis; Reviews and Press Releases 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Nightfall, David Goodis; Production 1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Nightsquad, David Goodis 1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Nothing in her Way, Charles Williams 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Nothing More than Murder, Jim Thompson 198-1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Only in L. A., Murray Sinclair 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- The Only Out is Death, Peter Rabe 1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Perversity, Francis Carco; Reviews and Press Releases 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Perversity, Francis Carco; Production 1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Pick-U, Charles Willeford 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Pick-Up, Charles Willeford; Reviews and Press Releases 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Pick-Up, Charles Willeford; Production 1987 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Population 1280, Jim Thompson 1983 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Population 1280, Jim Thompson; Reviews 1984 and 1989 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Population 1280, Jim Thompson; Advertising 1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Population 1280, Jim Thompson; Production 1984 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Port Tropique, Barry Gifford 1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Port Tropique, Barry Gifford 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Port Tropique, Barry Gifford; Reviews 1980-1981, 1986-1987, and 1989 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Port Tropique, Barry Gifford; Advertising No Date (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Port Tropique, Barry Gifford; Contract, ABI, etc. 1980, 1986-1988, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Port Tropique, Barry Gifford; Sub-Rights 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Recoil, Jim Thompson 1984 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Root of His Evil, James M. Cain 1987 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Running of Beasts, Bill Pronzini and Barry Malzberg 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Running of Beasts, Bill Pronzini and Barry Malzberg Reviews 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Running of Beasts, Bill Pronzini and Barry Malzberg Production 1988 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Savage Night, Jim Thompson 1984 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Seven Slayers, Paul Cain; Reviews: Fast One, Paul Cain; Reviews 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Seven Slayers, Paul Cain; Reviews 1988 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Shoot the Piano Player, David Goodis 1986 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Shoot the Piano Player, David Goodis; Reviews 1987 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Shoot the Piano Player, David Goodis; Production 1987 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Silk Stalkings, Susan Thompson and Victoria Nichols 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Silk Stalkings, Susan Thompson and Victoria Nichols; Contract 1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Silk Stalkings, Susan Thompson and Victoria Nichols; Advertising 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Silk Stalkings, Susan Thompson and VictoriaNichols; Production 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Silk Stalkings, Susan Thompson and Victoria Nichols; Production 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Silk Stalkings, Susan Thompson and Victoria Nichols; Reviews 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Sinful Woman, James M. Cain 1987 and 1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Sing Me a Murder, Helen Nielsen 1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Sing Me a Murder, Helen Nielsen; Review 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Sing Me a Murder, Helen Nielsen; Production 1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Straight Man, Kent Nelson 1978 and, 1987-1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Street of No Return, David Goodis 1986 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Street of No Return, David Goodis; Reviews 1988 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Strongarm, Dan Marlowe 1986 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Swamp Sister, Robert Edmund Alter 1985 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Swamp Sister, robert Edmund Alter Reviews 1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- A Swell-Looking Babe, Jim Thompson 1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- A Swell-Looking Babe, Jim Thompson; Reviews 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- A Ticket to Hell, Harry Whittington 1986 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- A Ticket to Hell, Harry Whittington; Reviews 1989 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Tough Luck L. A., Murray Sinclair 1987 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Tough Luck L. A., Murray Sinclair; Production 1988 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Truth of the Matter, John Lutz 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Truth of the Matter, John Lutz 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- The Vengeance Man, Dan Marlowe 1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Violent Saturday, W. L. Heath 1984 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Violent Saturday, W. L. Heath; Production 1955, (Xeroxed) (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Web of Murder, Harry Whittington 1986 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Web of Murder, Harry Whittington; Production 1987 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Web of Murder, Harry Whittington; Reviews and Press Release 1987 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Wild Town, Jim Thompson 1984 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Wild Town, Jim Thompson; Reviews 1986 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- You Play the Black and the Red Comes Up, Eric Knight 1985 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- You Play the Black and the Red Comes Up, Eric Knight; Reviews 1987 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Titles Under Consideration: Unpublished by Black Lizard 1959, 1961, 1962, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Logo poster and cover art from Never Live Twice: No Date, 2 copies of each (4 total) (Box Posters, Folder 1)